These rocks have been hitting our earth for about three billion years,
هذه الصخور كانت ترتطم بكوكب الأرض لحوالي ثلاثة مليارات سنة،
and are responsible for much of what’s gone on on our planet.
وهي مسئولة من كثير مما جرى على كوكبنا.
This is an example of a real meteorite,
هذا مثال لحجر نيزكي حقيقي،
and you can see all the melting of the iron
تستطيعون مشاهدة إنصهار الحديد
from the speed and the heat when a meteorite hits the earth,
من السرعة والحرارة عندما يرتطم النيزك بالأرض،
and just how much of it survives and melts.
والى أي مدى تبقى وتذوب.
From a meteorite from space,
من النيازك الى الفضاء،
we’re over here with an original Sputnik.
ونحن هنا مع أسبوتنيك الأصلي.
This is one of the seven surviving Sputniks that was not launched into space.
هذا أحد الأسبوتنيك السبعة الناجية التي لم تطلق الى الفضاء.
This is not a copy.
هذه ليست نسخة.
The space age began 50 years ago in October,
حقبة الفضاء بدأت قبل 50 عاماً مضت في أكتوبر،
and that’s exactly what Sputnik looked like.
وهذا بالضبط كيف بدى شكل أسبوتنيك.
And it wouldn’t be fun to talk about the space age
ولن يكون مرحاً الحديث عن حقبة الفضاء
without seeing a flag that was carried
بدون رؤية العلم الذي تم حمله
to the moon and back, on Apollo 11.
الى القمر و رجع ، على أبولو 11.
The astronauts each got to carry
حمل كل من رواد الفضاء
about ten silk flags in their personal kits.
حوالي عشرة أعلام من الحرير في حقائبهم الشخصية.
They would bring them back and mount them.
وسيقومون بإرجاعها وحفظها.
So this has actually been carried to the moon
إذاً هذا في الواقع تم حمله الى القمر
and back.
وعادوا به.
So that’s for fun.
إذاً هذا من أجل المرح.
The dawn of books is, of course, important.
بدايات الكتب، بالطبع، مهمة.
And it wouldn’t be interesting to talk about the dawn of books
ولن يكون مثيراً للإهتمام الحديث عن بدايات الكتب
without having a copy of a Guttenberg Bible.
بدون الحصول على إنجيل غتنبرغ.
You can see how portable and handy it was to have your own Guttenberg
يمكنكم ملاحظة كم كان عملياً و سهل الحمل أن يكون لديك نسختك الخاص من غتنبرغ
in 1455.
عام 1455.
But what’s interesting about the Guttenberg Bible, and the dawn of this technology,
لكن المثير حول إنجيل غتنبرغ هو بدايات هذه التكنلوجيا،
is not the book.
ليست الكتاب.
You see, the book was not driven by reading.
تشاهدون، لم يكن الكتاب مدفوعاً بالقراءة.
In 1455, nobody could read.
عام 1455، لا يستطيع شخص القراءة.
So why did the printing press succeed?
إذاً لماذا نجحت المطبعة ؟
This is an original page of a Guttenberg Bible.
هذه صفحة أصلية من إنجيل غتنبرغ.
So you’re looking here at one of the first printed books
إذاً فأنتم تنظرون هنا الى أحد أوائل الكتب المطبوعة
using movable type in the history of man,
بإستخدام نوع منقول من تاريخ الإنسان،
550 years ago.
قبل 550 عاماً مضت.
We are living at the age here at the end of the book,
نعيش الآن في عهد نهاية الكتب
where electronic paper will undoubtedly replace it.
حيث قامت الأوراق الإلكترونية بإحلال مكانها بلا شك.
But why is this so interesting? Here’s the quick story.
لكن لماذا هذا مهم للغاية؟ ها هي قصة سريعة.
It turns out that in the 1450s,
تبيّن أنه في أعوام 1450،
the Catholic Church needed money,
أرادت الكنيسة الكاثوليكية المال،
and so they
لذا فقد طبعوا تساهيل --
actually hand-wrote these things called indulgences,
في الواقع كتبوا بأيديهم هذه الاشياء المسماة تساهيل،
which were forgiveness’s on pieces of paper.
التي هي صكوك غفران من الورق.
They traveled all around Europe
التي أنتقلت كل أنحاء أوروبا
and sold by the hundreds or by the thousands.
وباعوا منها بالمئات أو بالآلاف.
They got you out of purgatory faster.
يخرجونك من العذاب بصورة أسرع.
And when the printing press was invented
وعندما تم إختراع المطبعة
what they found was they could print indulgences,
ما أدركوه كان أنه بمقدورهم طباعة التساهيل،
which was the equivalent of printing money.
التي كانت تكافئ طباعة الأموال.
And so all of Western Europe started buying printing presses in 1455 --
وعليه بدأت كل أوروبا الغربية في شراء المطابع عام 1455
to print out thousands,
لطباعة الآلالف
and then hundreds of thousands,
ثم مئات الآلالاف،
and then ultimately millions
ثم في نهاية المطاف الملايين
of single, small pieces of paper
لقطعة صغيرة من الورق
that got you out of middle hell and into heaven.
التي تنقلك من الجحيم الى الجنة.
That is why the printing press succeeded,
لهذا نجحت المطابع،
and that is why Martin Luther
ولهذا السبب قام مارتن لوثر
nailed his 90 theses to the door:
بتقديم اطروحاته التسعين الى الباب
because he was complaining that the Catholic Church had gone amok
لأنه كان يشكو من أن الكنيسة الكاثوليكية قد جن جنونها
in printing out indulgences and selling them
بطباعة التساهيل وبيعها
in every town and village and city in all of Western Europe.
في كل مدينة وقرية في كل أنحاء أوروبا الغربية.
So the printing press, ladies and gentlemen,
إذاً المطبعة، سيداتي وسادتي،
was driven entirely by the printing of forgivenesses
كانت مدفوعة في الأساس بطباعة الغفران
and had nothing to do with reading.
ولا علاقة لها بالقراءة.
More tomorrow. I also have pictures coming of the library
المزيد غداً. أيضاً لدي صور جاءت من المكتبة
for those of you that have asked for pictures.
لأؤلئك الذين سألوا عن الصور.
We’re going to have some tomorrow.
سنقوم بعرض بعضها غداً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Instead of showing an object from the stage
بدلاً عن عرض الشئ من المنصة
I’m going to do something special for the first time.
سأقوم بعمل شئ مميز لأول مرة.
We are going to show, actually, what the library looks like, OK?
سنقوم بعرض، في الواقع، ما تبدو عليه المكتبة، حسناً؟
So, I am married to the most wonderful woman in the world.
إذاً، أنا متزوج من أروع إمرأة في العالم.
You’re going to find out why in a minute,
سنعرف لماذا هذا خلال دقيقة،
because when I went to see Eileen,
لأنني عندما ذهبت للقاء آيلين،
this is what I said I wanted to build.
هذا ما قلت أنني أريد بناءه.
This is the Library of Human Imagination.
هذه مكتبة لخيال الإنسان.
The room itself is three stories tall.
الغرفة نفسها بطول ثلاثة طوابق.
In the glass panels are 5,000 years of human imagination
في ألواح زجاجية تقبع 5 آلالاف سنة من خيال الإنسان
that are computer controlled.
التي يتم التحكم بها عبر الكمبيوتر.
The room is a theatre. It changes colors.
الغرفة عبارة عن مسرح. تغيّر ألوانها.
And all throughout the library are different objects, different spaces.
وجميع أرجاء المكتبة أشياء مختلفة، ومسافات مختلفة.
It’s designed like an Escher print.
لقد صُممت مثل طباعة إيشر.
Here is some of the lower level of the library,
هنا بعض الأجزء السفلى للمكتبة
where the exhibits constantly change.
حيث تتغير المعروضات بإستمرار.
You can walk through. You can touch.
يمكننا المشي خلالها . يمكنك اللمس.
You can see exactly how many of these types of items would fit in a room.
يمكنك رؤية كم من أنواع هذه الأشياء يمكن أن تناسب غرفة.
There’s my very own Saturn V.
هذا كوكب زحل خاصتي .
Everybody should have one, OK? (Laughter)
ينبغي لكل شخص الحصول على خاصته، حسناً.
So you can see here in the lower level of the library
إذاً يمكنكم رؤية الجزء السفلي للمكتبة هنا
the books and the objects.
الكتب والمعروضات.
In the glass panels all along is sort of the history of imagination.
طوال لوحات الزجاج، هي نوع من تاريخ الخيال.
There is a glass bridge that you walk across
هناك جسر زجاجي يمكنك المشي عبره
that’s suspended in space.
ذلك معلّق في الفراغ.
So it’s a leap of imagination.
إذاً فهي قفزة في الخيال.
How do we create?
إذاً كيف نبدع ؟
Part of the question that I have answered is,
وجزء من السؤال الذي أجبته
is we create by surrounding ourselves with stimuli:
هو أن نبدع بإحاطة أنفسنا بالمحفزات،
with human achievement, with history,
بإنجازات الإنسانية، بالتاريخ،
with the things that drive us and make us human --
بالأشياء التي تحركنا وتجعلنا بشر.
the passionate discovery, the bones of dinosaurs long gone,
الإكتشاف العاطفي، عظام الديناصورات قبل زمن سحيق،
the maps of space that we’ve experienced,
خرائط الأمكنة التي خبرناها،
and ultimately the hallways that stimulate our mind and our imagination.
و في نهاية المطاف الممرات التي تحفز عقولنا وخيالنا.
So hopefully tomorrow I’ll show
إذاً ، آمل أن أريكم غداً
one or two more objects from the stage,
واحد أو أثنين من هذه الأشياء على المنصة،
but for today I just wanted to say thank you
لكن بالنسبة لليوم رغبت في أن أقول شكراً لكم
for all the people that came and talked to us about it.
لكل الناس الذين أتوا وتحدثوا معنا حولها.
And Eileen and I are thrilled to open our home
وأنا وآيلين في غاية السعادة لفتح بيتنا
and share it with the TED community.
وتقاسمه مع مجتمع تيد.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
TED is all about patterns in the clouds.
تيد يدور حول أنماط في السحب.
It’s all about connections.
الأمر كله عن التواصل.
It’s all about seeing things
الأمر كله عن رؤية الأشياء
that everybody else has seen before
التي شاهدها الجميع من قبل
but thinking about them in ways that nobody has thought of them before.
لكن التفكير بها بطرق لم يتطرق إليها أحد من قبل.
And that’s really what discovery and imagination is all about.
وهذا كل ما تدور حوله الإكتشافات والخيال.
For example, we can look
على سبيل المثال، يمكننا رؤية
at a DNA molecule model here.
نموذج جزيئ الحمض النووي هنا.
None of us really have ever seen one,
لم يرى أي منّا في الواقع هذا من قبل،
but we know it exists because we’ve been taught
لكننا نعلم أنه موجود لأنه تم تعليمنا
to understand this molecule.
فهم لماذا هذا الجزيئ.
But we can also look at an Enigma machine
لكن يمكننا أيضاً النظر لآلة أنيغما
from the Nazis in World War II
من النازيين في الحرب العالمية الثانية
that was a coding and decoding machine.
كانت آلة تقوم بتشفير وفك التشفير.
Now, you might say, what does this have to do with this?
الآن، ربما تقولون، ما علاقة هذا بهذا؟
Well, this is the code for life,
حسناً، هذه هي شفرة الحياة،
and this is a code for death.
وهذه شفرة الموت.
These two molecules
هذين الجزئين
code and decode.
تشفير وفك التشفير.
And yet, looking at them, you would see a machine and a molecule.
وحتى الآن، النظر إليهم، يمكنكم رؤية آلة وجزيئ.
But once you’ve seen them in a new way,
لكن بمجرد رؤيتكم لها بطريقة حديثة،
you realize that both of these things really are connected.
تدرك أن كلٌ من هذه الأشياء بالفعل متصلة.
And they’re connected primarily because of this here.
وهم موصولون في الاساس بسبب هذا هنا.
You see, this is a human brain model, OK?
تشاهدون، هذا نموذج لدماغ بشري، حسناً؟
And it’s rare, because we never really get to see a brain.
وأنه نادر، لأننا لم نتوصل لرؤية دماغ.
We get to see a skull. But there it is.
توصلنا لرؤية الجمجمة. لكن ذلك هو.
All of imagination -- everything that we think,
كل الخيال، كل شئ نفكر به،
we feel, we sense -- comes through the human brain.
نشعر به، نحس به، يأتي عبر الدماغ البشر.
And once we create new patterns in this brain,
وبمجرد أن ننشئ نمطاً جديداً في هذا الدماغ،
once we shape the brain in a new way,
بمجرد أن نشكّل الدماغ بطريقة جديدة،
it never returns to its original shape.
لن يرجع بتاتاً لشكله الأصلي.
And I’ll give you a quick example.
وسأقدم لكم مثالاً سريعاً.
We think about the Internet;
نفكر بالإنترنت.
we think about information that goes across the Internet.
نفكر بالمعلومات التي تمر عبر الإنترنت.
And we never think about the hidden connection.
ولم نفكر بتاتاً بالإتصالات الخفية.
But I brought along here a lump of coal --
لكني أحضرت هنا قطعة من الفحم --
right here, one lump of coal.
ها هنا، قطعة واحدة من الفحم.
And what does a lump of coal have to do with the Internet?
وما هي علاقة قطعة الفحم بالإنترنت؟
You see, it takes the energy in one lump of coal
تتابعون، يستهلك الأمر قطعة من الفحم
to move one megabyte of information across the net.
لنقل ميغابايت من المعلومات عبر الشبكة.
So every time you download a file,
لذا فكل مرة تقوم بتحميل ملف،
each megabyte is a lump of coal.
كل ميغابايت هي قطعة من الفحم.
What that means is, a 200-megabyte file
ماذا يعنيه ذلك، ملف حجمه 200 ميغابايت
looks like this, ladies and gentlemen. OK?
يبدو كهذا، سيداتي سادتي. حسناً؟
So the next time you download a gigabyte,
إذاً المرة القادمة التي تحمّلون غيغابايت،
or two gigabytes, it’s not for free, OK?
أو أثنين غيغابايت، أنها ليست مجانية، حسناً؟
The connection is the energy it takes to run the web ,
العلاقة هي الطاقة التي تستهلكها لتشغيل الويب
and to make everything we think possible, possible.
ولجعل كل شئ نظن أنه ممكن، ممكن.
Thanks, Chris.
شكراً، كريس.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)